Guide to the James Woodman Thompson papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
James Woodman Thompson Papers,
1909-1955
Thompson, James Woodman, 1889?-1955.
57,800 items (109 boxes, 5 pkgs, 12 map case drawers)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
4079398
Biographical Note
New York stage, costume, and scenic designer.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, documents, memorabilia, photographs, original drawings, sketches and studies, and printed materials of Thompson. Correspondence, mostly uncataloged, relating to purchases made in Spain, France, and Italy during 1928; documents; memorabilia; photographs; printed material including publicity, books, engravings, and reproductions; an illustration file containing source illustrations for architectural details, costumes -- subdivided by century, country, societal role, sex, age, and by countries, crafts, painting, styles, etc., and including some original Thompson drawings; a production file containing related correspondence and documents; miscellaneous commissioned projects; and Thompson Studies, including studies done by Thompson, his work as a student, and materials pertaining to his activities as a teacher.
Productions and miscellaneous commissioned projects contain one or more of the following items: correspondence; contracts (not Thompson's); expense itemizations; notes; property lists; costume lists; cast lists; schedules; rehearsal schedules; scripts; music "run-throughs;" programs; publicity; blueprints and other photo-reproductions of drawings; drawings, usually schematics or prop detail, done in pencil and/or ink; sketches, generally costume but some schematics, usually in pencil (costume sketches may have swatches of material attached and may be colored); rough sketches, often quite crude, usually schematics and construction, but also costume ideas (these are always in pencil); studies, usually in color: watercolors, poster paint, melted crayon, light oil, ink, and pencil (generally of backdrops or sets); cardboard miniature mock-ups, presumably for studies of different lighting effects; photographs of sets, scenes, and the cardboard mock-ups; and source illustrations and photographs for a particular production.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 13 series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Documents and Memorabilia
Series III: Printed Material
Series IV: Source Material
Series V: Illustration File
Series VI: Production File
Series VII: Miscellaneous Commissioned Projects
Series VIII: Thompson Studies
Series IX: Thompson the Student
Series X: Thompson the Teacher
Series XI: Production Files
Series XII: Thompson Studies
Series XIII: Additions
Subjects
Costume design.; Costume--Spain.; Costume--France.; Costume--Italy.; Architecture--Spain.; Architecture--France.; Architecture--Italy.; Theater.; Theaters--Stage-setting and scenery.; Drawings.; Engravings.; Illustrations.; Set designers.; Costume designers.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1971 M-71 Brander Matthews Dramatic Museum Transfer
- Series I: Correspondence
  [See also Map Cases]
  - Correspondence (Box A)
    [See also map cases]
- Series II: Documents and Memorabilia
  - Diplomas (High School and Carnegie Tech) -- Hofstra College Drama Club -- Photographs (of Woodman Thompson and of Thompson and an unidentified person) -- Tax material (1924 income, 1 sheet) (Box B)
    [See also map case]
- Series III: Printed Material
  - Publicity for Thompson's Productions, ( Scrapbook &Unsorted clippings, etc.) (Box B)
- Series IV: Source Material
  - Calendar for 1954 from Ciba of Switzerland (Box B)
  - Chinese Theater, N.Y. (a series of matted studies) (Box B)
  - Eleven prints of works of Albrecht Durer (Box B)
  - Albrecht Durer prints (torn from a book) (Box B)
  - Five engravings (Box B)
  - Prints: Park's New Characters - Twelfth Night Characters (Box B)
  - Prints: 200 of people; landscapes; assorted eras and cultures; divided Woodman Thompson into 3 groups (Box B)
  - Source Illustrations: L'Amour italien -- The Park Theater of 1822 -- Piano (Harpsichord?) -- "Umbragraph" (Box B)
  - Le Dix-neuvieme siécle, Les Moeurs Les Arts, Les Idees, [Paris?], [n.d.] (Box B)
  - Leonardo the Painter, [ n.p.]: L'Illustrazione Italiana, June 18, 1939 (Box B)
- Series V: Illustration File
  - Subseries V.1: Architecture
    - Architectural Details: Arabesques - Castles (Box 1)
    - Architectural Details: Ceilings - Gardens (Box 2)
    - Architectural Details: Gardens (Box 3)
    - Architectural Details: Halls - Moldings (Box 4)
    - Architectural Details: Musical Instruments - Schools (Box 5)
    - Architectural Details: Schools - Workshops (Box 6)
  - Subseries V.2: Costumes
    - Accessories (Box 7)
    - Particular A - O (Box 8)
    - Particular P - Z (Box 9)
    - Ancient Greek (Box 10)
    - Ancient Rome (Box 10)
    - Romanesque (several particular nations) (Box 10)
    - Medieval: Ecclesiastic, Military (Box 11)
    - 13th Cent.: English.; French; German; Italian; Spanish (Box 11)
    - 14th Cent.: Ecclesiastic; English; French; German; Italian (Box 11)
    - 14th Cent.: Italian; Spanish (Box 12)
    - 15th Cent. (1st half): English; Flemo-Dutch; French; German; Italian; Spanish (Box 12)
    - 15th Cent. (2nd half): English; Flemo-Dutch; French; German (Box 13)
    - 15th Cent. (2nd half): Italian; Spanish (Box 14)
    - 15th - 16th Cent. transition: Flemo-Dutch; German; Italian (Box 15)
    - 16th Cent.: Ecclesiastic; Military (Box 15)
    - 16th Cent. (1st half): English; Flemo-Dutch; French; German; Italian (Box 16)
    - 16th Cent. (1st half): Italian (Box 17)
    - 16th Cent. (2nd half): English; Flemo-Dutch; French; German (Box 17)
    - 16th Cent. (2nd half): Italian; Spanish (Box 18)
    - 17th Cent. (1st half): Ecclesiastic; Military; Theatrical; English; Flemo-Dutch (Box 18)
    - 17th Cent. (1st half): Flemo-Dutch (Box 19)
    - 17th Cent. (1st half): Italian; Spanish (Box 20)
    - 17th Cent (2nd half): English; Flemo-Dutch; French (Box 20)
    - 17th Cent (2nd half): French; German; Italian; Scandinavian; Spanish (Box 21)
    - 18th Cent.: Ecclesiastic; Illustrative; Military; Notes; Porcelain; Theatrical; English - men (Box 21)
    - 18th Cent.: English - women; English - children; English - genre; English - misc. artists (A-Z); English - artists (A-R) (Box 22)
    - 18th Cent.: English - artists (R-Z) (Box 23)
    - 18th Cent.: French - men; French - women; French - children; French - genre; French - Revolution; French - misc. artists; French - artists (A-C) (Box 23)
    - 18th Cent.: French - artists (D-Z); French - sculpture (Box 24)
    - 18th Cent.: Dutch (Box 24)
    - 18th Cent.: German - miscellaneous; German - artists (Box 24)
    - 18th Cent.: Italian - miscellaneous; Italian - artists (A-L) (Box 24)
    - 18th Cent.: Italian - artists (P-Z) (Box 25)
    - 18th Cent.:Polish; Russian; Scandinavian; Spanish (Box 25)
    - 19th Cent.: Eccelsiastic; Military; Miscellaneous (Box 25)
    - 1810s (Box 26)
    - 1820s (Box 26)
    - 1820s (Box 27)
    - 1830s (Box 27)
    - 1840s (Box 27)
    - 1840s (Box 28)
    - 1850s (Box 28)
    - 1850s (Box 29)
    - 1860s (Box 30)
    - 1870s (Box 30)
    - 1870s (Box 31)
    - 1880s (Box 31)
    - 1890s (Box 32)
    - 1890s (Box 33)
    - 20th Cent.: 1900s (Box 33)
    - 20th Cent.: Military (Box 34)
    - 20th Cent.: 1910s (Box 34)
    - Modern (1920s) (Box 35)
  - Subseries V.3: Countries
    - Africa (Box 35)
    - American Indian (Box 35)
    - American Negro (Box 36)
    - Arabia (Box 36)
    - Austria (Box 36)
    - Austria-Hungary (Box 36)
    - Balkans (Box 36)
    - Barbary (Box 37)
    - Belgium (Box 37)
    - British Isles (Box 37)
    - British Isles (Box 38)
    - Bohemia (Box 38)
    - Canada (Box 38)
    - Central America (Box 38)
    - China (Box 39)
    - Egypt (Box 40)
    - Eskimo (Box 40)
    - France (Box 40)
    - France (Box 41)
    - Germany (Box 41)
    - Germany (Box 42)
    - Greece (Box 42)
    - Holland (Box 42)
    - India (Box 42)
    - India (Box 43)
    - Indo-China (Box 43)
    - Indo-China (Box 44)
    - Italy (Box 44)
    - Italy (Box 45)
    - Japan (Box 45)
    - Mexico (Box 45)
    - Mexico (Box 46)
    - Norway (Box 46)
    - Pacific Islands (Box 46)
    - Palestine (Box 46)
    - Palestine (Box 47)
    - Persia (Box 47)
    - Portugal (Box 47)
    - Russia (Box 47)
    - Russia (Box 48)
    - Scandinavia (Box 48)
    - South America (Box 48)
    - Spain (Box 48)
    - Spain (Box 49)
    - Switzerland (Box 50)
    - Syria (Box 50)
    - Turkestan (Box 50)
    - Turkey (Box 50)
    - U. S. A. (Box 50)
    - West Indies (Box 51)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 51)
  - Subseries V.4: Crafts
    - Unsorted (Box 51)
    - Bookbinding (Box 51)
    - Curtains (Box 51)
    - Glass (Box 51)
    - Glass (Box 52)
    - Heraldry (Box 52)
    - Illuminated manuscripts (Box 52)
    - Ironwork (Box 52)
    - Lace (Box 52)
    - Leather (Box 52)
    - Letters (Box 52)
    - Money (Box 52)
    - Musical instruments (Box 52)
    - Paper - mache (Box 52)
    - Picture frames (Box 53)
    - Pottery (Box 53)
    - Pottery (Box 54)
    - Pottery (Box 55)
    - Printing (Box 55)
    - Prints (Box 55)
    - Rugs (Box 55)
    - Silver (Box 55)
    - Silver (Box 56)
    - Stained glass (Box 56)
    - Stoves (Box 56)
    - Tapestries (Box 56)
    - Tapestries (Box 57)
    - Textiles (Box 57)
    - Tiles (Box 58)
    - Title pages (Box 58)
    - Tole (Box 58)
    - Vehicle (Box 58)
    - Wall paper (Box 58)
    - Water coloring (Box 58)
    - Weaving (Box 58)
    - Miscllaneous (Box 58)
  - Subseries V.5: Painting
    - Drawings (Box 59)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 59)
    - Perspectives (Box 59)
    - Still life (Box 59)
    - Murals (Box 59)
    - Portraits (Box 59)
    - American (Box 60)
    - British (Box 60)
    - British (Box 61)
    - French (Box 61)
    - French (Box 62)
    - German (Box 62)
    - Italian (Box 63)
    - Russian (Box 63)
    - Scandinavian (Box 63)
    - Trees & Landscapes (Box 63)
  - Subseries V.6: Styles
    - Primitive Nan (Box 63)
    - Ancient Western Asia (Box 63)
    - Ancient Egypt (Box 63)
    - Ancient Egypt (Box 64)
    - Ancient Rome (Box 64)
    - Ancient Rome (Box 65)
    - Biblical (Box 65)
    - Byzantine-Romanesque (Box 65)
    - Byzantine-Romanesque (Box 66)
    - Romanesque (Box 67)
    - Islamic (Box 67)
    - Gothic (Box 67)
    - Gothic (Box 68)
    - Gothic Architecture - exteriors (Box 68)
    - Gothic Architecture - details (Box 68)
    - Gothic Architecture - miscellaneous (Box 69)
    - Gothic Architecture - ecclesiastic (Box 69)
    - Gothic Architecture - ecclesiastic (Box 70)
    - Gothic Architecture - interiors (Box 70)
    - Gothic Architecture - furniture (Box 70)
    - Gothic Architecture - furniture (Box 71)
    - Renaissance - miscellaneous (Box 71)
    - Renaissance - English (Box 71)
    - Renaissance - Flemo-Dutch (Box 71)
    - Renaissance - French (Box 71)
    - Renaissance - French (Box 72)
    - Renaissance - French (Box 73)
    - Renaissance - German (Box 73)
    - Renaissance - Italian (Box 73)
    - Renaissance - Italian (Box 74)
    - Renaissance - Scandinavian (Box 74)
    - 17th Cent.: miscellaneous (Box 74)
    - 17th Cent.: American (Box 74)
    - 17th Cent.: Flemo-Dutch (Box 75)
    - 17th Cent.: German (Box 75)
    - 17th Cent.: Italian (Box 75)
    - 17th Cent.: Scandinavian (Box 75)
    - 17th Cent. (1st half): English (Box 75)
    - 17th Cent. (1st half): French (Box 75)
    - 17th Cent. (2nd half): English (Box 75)
    - 17th Cent. (2nd half): English (Box 76)
    - 17th Cent. (2nd half): French (Box 76)
    - 18th Cent.: American (Box 76)
    - 18th Cent.: American (Box 77)
    - 18th Cent.: Colonial American (Box 77)
    - 18th Cent.: Dutch (Box 77)
    - 18th Cent.: English (Box 78)
    - 18th Cent.: English (Box 79)
    - 18th Cent.: French (Box 79)
    - 18th Cent.: French - Louis XV (Box 79)
    - 18th Cent.: French - Provincial (Box 79)
    - 18th Cent.: French - Louis XVI (Box 80)
    - 18th Cent.: French - Directoire (Box 80)
    - 18th Cent.: German (Box 80)
    - 18th Cent.: Italian (Box 81)
    - 18th Cent.: Miscellaneous (Box 81)
    - 19th Cent.: French - Miscellaneous (Box 81)
    - 19th Cent.: French - Empire (Box 81)
    - Victorian (Box 82)
    - Victorian (Box 83)
    - Victorian (Box 84)
    - 1900 (Box 84)
    - Modern (Box 84)
    - Modern (Box 85)
  - Subseries V.7: Miscellaneous
    - Animals (Box 85)
    - Animals (Box 86)
    - Costumes (Box 86)
    - Exteriors (Box 87)
    - Functions (Box 87)
    - Functions (Box 88)
    - Illustrations (Box 88)
    - Illustrations (Box 89)
    - Illustrations (Box 90)
    - Industrial (Box 90)
    - Lighting (Box 90)
    - Old England, A Pictorial Museum, (2 Volumes, ) (Box 91)
    - Photographs Postcards (Box 92)
    - Props (Box 93)
    - Props (Box 94)
    - Props (Box 95)
    - Props (Box 96)
    - Shipping (Box 96)
    - Shipping (Box 97)
    - Theatre (Box 97)
    - Vehicles (Box 97)
    - Vehicles (Box 98)
    - War (Box 98)
    - War (Box 99)
    - War (Box 100)
    - Misellaneous (Box 101)
    - Miscellaneous Costume (ORIGINALS) (Box 102)
- Series VI: Production File
  Boxes 103 to 106 [See also Map Cases] -- Contains: correspondence; contracts; expenses; notes; property lists; costume lists; cast lists; schedules; scripts; music "run throughs"; programs; publicity; blueprints; drawings, usually schematics or prop details, done in pencil and/or ink; sketches, generally costume, but some schematics; rough sketches in pencil; studies in color (watercolor, poster paint, melted crayon, light oil, ink and pencil) usually for sets; cardboard minature mock-ups; photographs of sets, scenes, and mock-ups; source illustrations.
  - Unidentified material
  - Contracts (arranged chronologically)
  - The Admiral
  - The Adventures of Samuel Pickwick, Esq.
  - Antigone
  - Augustan Comedy (also called "A Neoclassical Comedy")
  - Balle Comique
  - The Beggar On Horseback
  - The Bishop Misbehaves
  - Bridal Quilt
  - Butterflies
  - Candida
  - Carioca Purple
  - The Chastening
  - Christopher Rand
  - Close Harmony (also called "Soft Music")
  - The Cocoanuts
  - Daisies Won't Tell
  - Dangerous Corner
  - Daphnis & Chloe
  - Deep River
  - Delicate Justice
  - Desert Song (also called "Lady Fair")
  - Expressing Willie
  - The Firebrand
  - The Ghost of Yankee Doodle
  - God Loves Us
  - The Habitual Husband
  - Hedda Gabler
  - Hospitality
  - In the Meantime
  - Iolanthe
  - Ipinegia aus Tarus
  - Joan d'Arc
  - Lightnin'
  - Little Theater Concert
  - Macbeth
  - The Magnificent Yankee
  - Malvaloca
  - The Marriage of Figaro
  - The Merchant of Venice
  - Midnight
  - Month In The Country
  - Neighbors
  - Nepenthe
  - The New Englander
  - Old Man Minick
  - Pirates Of Penzance
  - Plumes In The Dust
  - The Potters
  - A Primer For Lovers
  - Pure In Heart
  - Queen Victoria
  - Rhapsody Negro
  - Richard The Third (John Carradine)
  - The Rivals
  - Roger Bloomer
  - Romeo and Juliet
  - Rye
  - She Stoops To Conquer
  - The Shelf
  - The Squall
  - Sweet Nell Of Old Drury
  - Taboo
  - Theme And Variations
  - These Few Ashes
  - This One Man (also called "The Man Saul", etc.)
  - Tomorrow Is A Holiday
  - Venus Vixtrix
  - The Warrior's Husband
  - "What Price Glory?"
  - White Wings
  - "Why Not?"
  - "Will You Marry Me?"
  - The Winged Messenger
  - The Wisdom Tooth
  - The Wolf At The Door
  - Miscellaneous Productions -- Programs only
- Series VII: Miscellaneous Commissioned Projects
  [See also Map Cases] -- Contains: correspondence; contracts; expenses; notes; property lists; costume lists; cast lists; schedules; scripts; music "run throughs"; programs; publicity; blueprints; drawings, usually schematics or prop details, done in pencil and/or ink; sketches, generally costume, but some schematics; rough sketches in pencil; studies in color (watercolor, poster paint, melted crayon, light oil, ink and pencil) usually for sets; cardboard minature mock-ups; photographs of sets, scenes, and mock-ups; source illustrations.
  - The Chapin School (Box 107)
  - Costume design for Miss Houston (Box 107)
  - Costume Design for Miss Mae Murray (Box 107)
  - The Gotham Hotel Project (Box 107)
  - The Storm King School (Box 107)
  - The Surf Club (Box 107)
  - Weber and Heilbroner (Box 107)
- Series VIII: Thompson Studies
  - "Discarded Drawings" (Box 107)
  - Empire Costumes (Box 107)
  - Oriental-style watercolors (Box 107)
  - Still-life pencil drawings (Box 107)
- Series IX: Thompson the Student
  - "Egyptian and Assyrian costumes by Houston and Hornblower" (Box 107)
    [More than just Egyptian and Assyrian material; all near-eastern]
  - French Intimate Court History (notes and drawings) (Box 107)
  - Notebook (Box 107)
  - Old schoolwork: charcoal, watercolor (Box 107)
- Series X: Thompson the Teacher
  - "Chats on Costume" (Box 107)
  - Thompson teaching (correspondence between W.T. and people wishing to study for the union exam with him; sample exam items; sample work of students correspondence with union officials, etc.) (Box 107)
- Series XI: Production Files
  - "The Merchant of Venice." (Box 14-10-7)
  - "Chinese Theatre. N.Y." (Box 14-10-8)
  - "Augustan Comedy." (Box 14-10-8)
  - Miscellaneous material (Box 14-10-8)
  - "Unidentified Material." (Box 14-10-9)
  - "The Beggar on Horseback." (Box 14-10-9)
  - "The Bishop Misbehaves" - "The Chastening." (Box 14-10-10)
  - "Christopher Rand" - "Daphnis & Chloe." (Box 14-11-1)
  - "Deep River" - "God Loves Us." (Box 14-11-2)
  - "The Habitual Husband" - "Macbeth." (Box 14-11-3)
  - "The Magnificent Yankee" - "Neighbors." (Box 14-11-4)
  - "Nepenthe" - "Queen Victoria." (Box 14-11-5)
  - "Rhapsody Negro" - "Rye." (Box 14-11-6)
  - "The Shelf" - "Venus Vixtrix." (Box 14-11-7)
  - "The Warrior's Husband" - "Why Not?" (Box 14-11-8)
  - "The Winged Messenger" - "The Wolf At The Door." (Box 14-11-9)
  - Miscellaneous Commissioned Projects. (Box 14-11-9)
- Series XII: Thompson Studies
  - Documents; Memorabilia; Photographs; Printed Materials; Source Material (Box 14-11-10)
- Series XIII: Additions
  - "Beggar on Horseback" ["The Cady Home"], [n.p.], 1933, (15 x 22 3/4 Gouache) (Box 14-11-7)
    [From the Brander Matthews Dramatic Museum, 1970. Transferred from Art Properties, 23 September 2001]
  - "The Firebrand" Acts I and III, [n.p.], [ca. 1930], (15 1/2 x 22 1/2 Watercolor (signed on back)) (Box 14-11-7)
  - "Romeo and Juliet" Act I, scene i, [n.p.], 1933, (14 1/2 x 22 1/4 Watercolor) (Box 14-11-7)
  - "Scene from What Price Glory" Act II, [n.p.], [n.d.], (15 x 23 Watercolor) (Box 14-11-7)
    [Inscribed on verso: "What Price Glory"/ Scene II The Dugent/Designed by/Woodman Thompson/for Arthur Hopkins. From the Brander Matthews Dramatic Museum, 1970. Transferred from Art Properties, 23 September 2001]